holotalk and profiles in holography is
brought to you through the generous
support of the international holography
fund for more information visit their
website at holographyfund.org
[Laughter]
[Music]
hello Martinez this is Frank de Freitas
I would love to do it how about you yeah
that sounds great you're there at the
center today right yep what's your
responsibility there are you putting a
show in for yourself or something or
what well I've actually got a two-year
work permit to come and work over here
now oh okay I'm working on my PhD and
finishing that off and at the same time
setting up the stereo printing system
here at the holographic Center uh
helping with exhibitions just general
assistance around the place yeah
what's the stereo printer that you have
there uh it's a system that is
developed three years ago okay 30 by 40
from digital images that uses an LCD
screen wow
yeah so that I mean most of my work is
based on digital imaging is based on
taking photographs and mapping them
that's why I must
do now what do you do when you do these
stereograms do you do multiple
perspectives so that the scene comes out
three-dimensional or is the dimensional
quality of the scene not important to
you
these are important but it's not just
spatial Dimensions so what I'm looking
at is dimensions of times and some
movement within the scene and other
relationships so what I'll often do is
I'll I'll photograph something with with
maybe a person that stays in the same
space spot and everything else moved
okay or I might use a building or part
of the landscape as my as my visual
anchor and everything else is dynamic
around it and you work basically with
white light transmission holography
right a lot of white light transmission
my favorite combination is to do a full
Parallax stereo master and then do a
reflection transfer oh really that's my
favorite combination that's why I'm here
in New York I saw some pictures from an
exhibit of yours at the hollow center
and there were a number of your
Holograms that were on the wall and I
couldn't quite tell whether they were
rainbow Holograms with mirrored backing
or whether they were reflection
Holograms okay
worked since 2006. I think that's the
one percent of the holographic card
there were two pieces that were the the
three slit rainbows yeah
the mirror backing okay and then there
was uh one piece that was a reflection
a few pieces were cut in a chain link
fence as well yes that was a project
from 2004. and I often think about
holography as relating to pinhole
photography okay because
you know in pinhole photography you're
not you're not using a land
you're taking this tiny little point
source and expanding it out and in
holography you're not using a lens yes
rather than taking that tiny little
point so if you're you're using the the
very ordered reference piece and the
lighter the laser is it true that your
background is in physics
yes that's interesting so you're
combining both physics and art
absolutely and you approach it that way
as well you don't consider it one or the
other do you not just I mean I think in
the process of Designing a hologram
you're just I'm designing both from what
I know the light can do what I can
record and also kind of pushing and
questioning that asking myself could I
use this geometry what would what would
what will my image look like if I try
this this part process
um as well as you know I've got a real
interest in photography and image
collection and almost the the images we
make in our heads
[Music]
don't believe anything you think
it's probably a good idea do you find it
frustrating that holography so
polarizing when you get out there to do
presentations and speak to people
because sometimes someone will either
think that you're a scientist or
sometimes people will think or a group
will think that you're an artist
rarely can you convince anyone that
you're both
yeah it is
I think that comes from this this human
nature is that we want to put things in
boxes and
um and I think holography is one of
those mediums it doesn't fit into any
box very nicely
and that's why that's why I love working
because you're you're not doing one
thing all the time you're doing
different things but it means that I
mean some I mean some people sort of
want you to go and research and make the
most amazing technical hologram or some
people don't understand why you're
considering the technical aspects of it
why it is making art uh and yeah I
quite understand why people want to put
me into one of those boxes
sometimes when I I you know sometimes
I'll just tell people I do something
else to make them perfect
which way do you find it's more
acceptable
imagine that would depend on the graphic
your area that you're in but when you're
in the United States do you find people
approach you more from the scientific
aspect of holography or from the
artistic end of holography
interestingly when I'm here I'm I'm just
an artist
um part of that is I'm staying with a
group of artists uh in a warehouse in
New York City okay uh as a center for
holographic Arts I'm I'm I'm I'm I'm I'm
I'm doing what you would do in any sort
of Arts Administration organization uh
and so people just assume that I'm an
artist and what's interesting is when
I'm in Australia where I'm around a lot
of people who knew me while I was going
through my Physics degree and who uh and
other artists who actually set me up for
technical help in their you know their
video projection or their geometry
um I'm much more considered as a
physicist so I think it's it's just it's
what people see you doing yeah if they
see you in a gallery they're going to
think you're an artist if they see you
in lab they're going to think you're
you're a scientist yeah
I'm hearing an awful lot about
holography in Australia it seems to be
I mean holography in Australia was
always very well known but lately it's
been a lot of hologography news and
exhibits and work coming out of
Australia is there something happening
there that's become giving it a little
bit of a boom yeah what's what's really
funny about that there's I think it's
five or six of us in Australia in my
Holograms so we have meetings Australian
holographers and we have and we get
sandwiches and sit around a picnic bench
um that's nice
it's very nice Margaret Banyan who yes
you'll know um she moved to Australia
she's she's there and she's she's very
supportive you know she flew down to
Melbourne just to see my exhibition and
just to be there and just just to
encourage you know what's going on and
then Amy Rose has finished sinisters
Paula and Sydney she was on the show
recently yep and so she took her Masters
exhibition and she's been Touring that
around
um I exhibit probably about twice a year
in Australia
and so between that that's actually
quite a lot of holography going on and
most people I show Holograms to in
Australia it's the first time they've
seen a hologram still even into
yeah that's crazy that's crazy it's
crazy and it's I mean we've got we've
got the credit card Holograms but the
the the the the the kind of the mass
that 1970s kind of uh an early 80s wave
of holography that was in America didn't
quite reach Australia
um and that means that people people
don't know so quite so much about the
holography and it means they're a little
bit more open to it as well people don't
know what to expect you probably still
have people here in the states that are
seeing holograms for the first time
yeah and particularly in my generation
you know we just we we sort of we just
missed that National Geographic and that
first boom
[Music]
um and so you know we got with
experience we had from of holograms was
sort of representations on children's TV
shows and Star Wars and so we only saw
holograms on TV yeah which doesn't
really uh show you what a hologram's all
about yeah
then we have to continuously ask
holographers deal with that
misconception of holography too oh
absolutely yeah yeah I I think that's I
mean I think that's something
you're you're coming up against and uh
it's funny I've had shows in the
newspaper and they've been listed you
know in the Arts page as you know aren't
uh painting visual art and they make a
new category for it
um because they're not really quite sure
where to put it and they don't they
don't quite know what this medium is yet
are we all got to be dead and buried by
the time people finally understand this
and accept it
actually I don't think so because in
some ways holography has slipped into
our culture in ways that we don't really
even monitor anymore and the way that we
use the internet the way that we use
programs like Flickr the way I don't
know if you've seen Microsoft's new
program Sea Dragon which searches
through uh photos on the internet and
makes 3D scenes oh really no I have not
had a chance to see that
thank goodness yeah you've got you've
got these kind of uh these these hot
this holographic approach to Imaging
that's that that's that's within our
culture and that we we're experiencing
uh well I think what most people don't
understand is that that Holograms are a
physical structure and to to have the
awareness of optical structures uh I
think I think that that ties into
Holograms okay
Computing photonic crystals people
people will understand Holograms more
and more
probably become part of their lives as a
background more than the Forefront
absolutely you know we won't even know
that Holograms are working in the
background you know probably oh
absolutely yeah and I think I mean one
of the things I really like doing is I I
like working on a large scale so my aim
is to make holograms for public
and I really want to I really want to
bring Holograms into our cities and into
our into our into our daily lives where
where we can enjoy that that Dynamic
that the medium gives us yeah yeah do
you ever feel that you're not quite
achieving what some of the older artists
have achieved like my wife and I went
down to the Museum of Art in
Philadelphia and we saw
the Monet and we saw Rembrandt and
take a look at the work and the detail
that's in their work and then you
compare it to a reflection hologram and
sometimes I I personally feel that uh
really not more much more than you know
clicking a shutter or something and what
what talent is really in holography
my process is a very long process so I
to mainly because I go out and I
collected
is and I'm often building and making the
system
[Music]
and then installing it in terms of
competitive I mean to compared to those
Old Masters they they had I mean
painting is such a beautiful
and you're spending this time and you're
focused and you can't fake it either you
can't fake it
um with a hologram that there is there
is though that that possibility of uh
particularly with the the integral
Holograms and the multiplex Holograms
are really getting a lot of fish
information into them and if
if you know as we're starting to deal
with more and more on mortgage visual
information and more and more images to
really be able to design and structure
those images
it's it's more process of almost an
architecture or or a shaping that's
important with these Holograms I see
I see that sort of compositional side
from the from the very beginning of the
process to the installation really
did I read properly that you're very
interested in the study of urban type of
Art
is your subject or is that just a a
facet of
yes I I mean I live in the urban
environment I I've grown up within Urban
culture I you know I go out into nature
and I don't feel like making I feel like
just being I feel like walking through
the trees and you know I I maybe maybe
I'd move a rock that would be about the
extent of it but within the urban
landscape there's there's so much uh
mending and making and building and
beautifying that needs to be done
and you I mean the way the light plays
across the buildings I love New York
City it's just it's it's visually
spectacular Ages Every Day uh and it and
it and it wants to be captured into
images
so that's I think that's where I get a
lot of my inspiration from just walking
through the cities what was the 10 year
old Martina like
if you
could the 10 year old Martina had was uh
I think a little bit in shock because
she just moved from Sydney to Melbourne
and been pulled out of primary school
and had to make new friends but uh I'd
say probably the the the seven the
nine-year-old Martina got our first
camera
[Applause]
um and the seven-year-old Martina was
allowed to play in the dark room and so
what I do is I'd collect these objects
from around the house and I make Shadow
grounds often and I thought this was
um and I I was a very creative messy
child you know I was building drum
machines out of jam jar lids and I just
wanted to make and play and I don't
think I actually
so you constructed a lot of the things
that you used to produce whatever it was
that your creativity was calling for
absolutely interesting
object-based telegraphy as well is you
can you know you get to build these
these sculptures and then you record
them into Holograms and I always feel a
bit sad once I've recorded the Hologram
because I'm never quite sure what I'm
meant to do with the sculpture
sculpture
um yeah because they're usually just
sort of these bits of junks I've put
together
so and the Hologram then is what what I
give on to somebody else whose work in
holography inspired you
oh
um I I love Andy Pepper's Shadow grams
okay uh I love really workouts the all
these water ones and his waves
uh some of David pisanelli and Patrick
Boyd's early stereograms that's gorgeous
yes
um and Patrick did some of those when he
was
when he was York yep
it's hand registered
registered and very similar to the old
uh lithographic printing presses like
the heidelbergs were all of your Siam
magenta yellow and
yellow and he registered all the plates
absolutely yeah and they're they're that
I mean we often talk about holography
being very difficult and very hard and
then I I talked to some of my friends
who worked in print making and other art
mediums and they're just technical or
you might not have the vibration issue
or we might not have this issue but you
know you're still you're still dealing
with very technical museums they were at
one time
Hands-On tactical at least I think well
I don't know see I get confused I don't
know I mean you take someone who has to
do color correction and has to do hand
registration of printing plates and
things of that nature to do
side proofs and things like that in the
printing
and uh at one time that was all done by
hand and now it's not done by hand so is
there is it still just as much a craft
because it's not done
craft now
now I confused well I think we've got
the same issue with holography and
that's uh that some people still do it
by hand as an art form as a medium yeah
I don't think I would ever stop doing it
by hand exactly I just I just would not
it's like like a cabinet maker yep you
know I I wouldn't want to have a
computerized uh wood lathe cutting the
legs for a table I'd have to cut them my
myself you know
you know but when you're putting 1 800
images into a hologram I'm happy for my
computer to do it for me
I mean you're still doing a lot of work
to get that print what is that magic
number I've heard that reference so many
times 1080 images why that number oh is
it divided 360 or something is that
what's doing it for me for me comes
across because uh when I was in Cologne
at the uh the khm I they've got the a
lot of the uh the systems that come from
the Dutch holographic lab has 200 images
across okay
um and then what I was doing was I was
doing uh three three lines
[Music]
um and then what uh it was a it was I
was tweaking the system so I'd offset my
three lines three times so I was having
a nine
nine sort of rows okay and then 200
columns I see and that was giving me my
images the DHL is that Walter spearings
yes
contacted him a while ago to get on the
show and I I start to get him on here
I'll do it and I I've I've only used his
like sort of systems that have I mean
I'd love to see what he's working on now
because I've only used his system when
they're quite old and
old and they're they're gorgeous they're
really easy to print with you get great
results from them
and it means that you can really spend a
lot more time thinking about the
composition yeah you know they have
these bread competitions in France where
the only thing you're allowed to use for
breaking the bread
water
yeast
flour
that's all you're allowed to use and
everyone who enters those yearly
competitions are all baking their loaves
of bread all types of different loaves
of bread that come out differently are
all using those three ingredients what
do you think
your limitations would be or if there
would even be limitations if you were to
work with holography where all you had
was your isolation table your laser and
a spatial filter
oh I mean you could make so many
Holograms I I did a lot of work early on
with broken glass so getting pieces of
broken glass and uh you can you can use
the glass almost to shape the light and
it means that you've got almost like
multiple reference beams
I've done a lot of hand animation oh did
you put the glass in the reference beam
you say yeah you can start putting bits
of glass in your app you can sort of
tweet uh tweak your reference beam a
little bit and tweak your object
both of them are quite a little bit
interesting but most of them are fairly
uh a fairly uniform at the same time
yeah
you can get some very beautiful patterns
uh I've done a lot of Animation as well
with hand cutting stencils okay uh
recording that into it how many holds
you've you have a large body of work
don't you
it's funny I I always think I don't but
I have been I I when I I have been
solidly producing work now for about
eight
wow that's a lot for eight years thank
you um
I mean the last few years I sort of work
on a yearly printing cycle so I've been
I've been sort of collecting I mean
these are for my digital uh digital
analog hybrid I have to say
is taking them to Germany and making my
masters and taking them to New York and
making me transfer
um I also have been working in Korea at
the Korean holiday okay yeah yeah and
just finished setting up their
stereogram system there which uses 35
millimeter black and white film I saw
photos of you at one of the openings
there yeah
that's quite a spectacular
that certainly was yeah that was
fantastic but so I mean I mean I had to
travel to do my work but that it really
focuses me so I might have only two or
three weeks or a month in a play
but I'm going to make
Holograms I just make what I can in that
time
um and so it's not a lot of my year that
I spend printing but when I'm Printing
and printing yeah
yeah I will put a link to your website
on the holotalk page so people can click
on that and go over and and see your
your work excellent and I'll let you
know I have a an exhibition in my bags I
just need to laminate and install and
I'm hoping to have it in New York and
sometime in November so I'll let you
know about that as well November I would
say yeah okay it's not confirmed at the
moment but I'll I'll keep you informed
yeah so you sort of open up the hollow
center and take care of things on the
weekends for visit
we're open when we have shows on we'll
open every Saturday from 12 to 5 but we
also really encourage people if they're
coming to New York if they want to pop
in so just give us a call or send us an
email and we can set up appointments
Yeah Anna Maria and Rudy they have their
show there now yep it's up for one more
week one more week and then what's
coming in after that we've got Adrian
Klein coming in and sure oh really yes I
was just thinking of him the other night
yeah I saw many of his pieces
at the Museum of holography in New York
and how unfortunate he was killed in a
in an accident
in North Africa or something is that
correct okay now we're talking about
different people oh I'm sorry I thought
you said Adrian lines I'm Adrian Klein
oh I'm sorry she's an artist who works
with uh she's got some videos as well as
some Holograms okay but I'm gonna I'm
gonna look up Adrian Lyons now and have
a look at his work have you heard of
Adrian limes no oh oh this goes back
many many many many many many years has
to be
I'm guessing late 70s early 80s
but he was a wonderful holographer out
of Great Britain yeah and uh
unfortunately he died way too young
[Music]
some nice pieces that would
be photography I apologize to your other
artists that's okay I'm sure I'm sure
she won't mind at all but everybody will
remember her now yeah absolutely
Klein right okay all right well Martina
do me a favor how do you pronounce your
last name
a tricky one uh the pronunciation you've
got to sort of hide Dr so it's Mongolian
mongovius okay I read about people but
unless I've heard someone say their name
or heard someone else say the name I
have a very hard time you know figuring
out how to say a few names my name's
difficult very few people I sort of took
me get it right and it took me a few
years to learn how to spell it so sorry
all right well it was very nice having
you on the show was there anything that
you 'd like to have included that I
didn't ask you about
what would you like to say to folks if
you didn't have to respond to me asking
you something and you could just choose
to say whatever you wanted to say
I thought I'd really encourage people to
you know sort of have an open creative
attitude towards holography and that
there's there's different aspects of it
and there's different ways of thinking
about it and to allow it to be
incorporated into other aspects of their
life and just I think there's a lot in
holographic Imaging that we can all
learn about
[Music]
say have it degraded into other aspects
of their life what are you referring to
with that I think the approach of of
what of understanding what a holographic
image is I see understanding the way
that Optical like I think we live in
such an Information Society and we've
got very locked into digital information
oh God I'm just yeah I own yeah this
this collective intelligence that the
web's supposed to be turning I'm still
waiting for the intelligence part of the
day
yeah it's it's quite strange so sort of
a and there's there's an element element
of other types of information that's
kind of been forgotten about yeah and if
we look in the world around us uh you
know and the materials that we use and
the way that we interact with things
there's an information content in
everything and whether that's a light
whether that's material
and I think that's something that we
need to become more and more aware of as
we're getting into nanotechnology and
these Optical ways of communicating
information all the infrared and all the
Wireless Systems we've got and so to
really understand that sort of that that
great example
to implement the world wow it's not just
ones and zeros on your computer that's
most certainly is not
I will say that perhaps I can get into
New York and stop by the center and see
everybody it's probably about time that
I do that yep all right thank you so
much Martina I'll have this up probably
uh
say Monday because my
people listen to it when I put it up on
the weekends because they have other
things going on at least they should
have other things going
all right
take care nice speaking with you bye